<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>_Biomphalaria havanensis_ | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/_biomphalaria-havanensis_/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/_biomphalaria-havanensis_/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>_Biomphalaria havanensis_</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>_Biomphalaria havanensis_</title>
      <link>/tag/_biomphalaria-havanensis_/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Trematode Risk Through Host Control</title>
      <link>/project/trematode-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/trematode-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trematode parasite outbreaks are are detrimental to the catfish aquaculture industry. &lt;em&gt;Bolbophorus damnificus&lt;/em&gt; is the most common trematode parasite encountered in southeastern US catfish production. The complex life cycle of &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; includes a snail (first intermediate host), catfish (second intermediate host), and the American White Pelican &lt;em&gt;Pelecanus erythrorhynchos&lt;/em&gt; (final/tertiary host). The American White Pelican is a federally-protected species, limiting the options for management, and there are currently no approved therapeutics for trematode infections in catfish. Thus, the snail is the most viable target of &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; management. &lt;em&gt;P. trivolvis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. havanensis&lt;/em&gt; are common cohabitants in catfish aquaculture ponds and each can serve as the snail host in the &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; life cycle. We are working to better understand snail populations in these ponds to better inform treatment and management plans. Additionally, we are investigating natural and chemical methods/regimens to safely control snail populations as a way of reducing &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; risk on catfish production facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
