<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>catfish | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/catfish/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/catfish/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>catfish</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>catfish</title>
      <link>/tag/catfish/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating nanopore sequencing for microbial community characterization in catfish pond water</title>
      <link>/publication/pond-microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pond-microbiome/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rotenone Has Little Effect on Water Quality, Phytoplankton, Zooplankton, or Macroinvertebrates in Aquaculture Nursery Ponds</title>
      <link>/publication/rotenone/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rotenone/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Activation of Henneguya ictaluri Actinospores by Nonictalurid Fish Species, with Implications for Management of Proliferative Gill Disease in Catfish Aquaculture</title>
      <link>/publication/gambusia-pgd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/gambusia-pgd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity in catfish production ponds</title>
      <link>/project/ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Approximately 50% of U.S.-raised catfish production takes place in the state of Mississippi. Catfish production occurs in earthen ponds where many natural processes still occur. With this production setup, natural pond inhabitants must be included in the understanding of the pond environment and how their presence, behaviors, and ecology effect the production of catfish. Many macroinvertebrates can be nuisance species at various periods within the production cycle. For instance, dragonfly nymphs can heavily predate on catfish fry after stocking of ponds for fingerling production. Meanwhile, other macroinvertebrates serve as intermediate hosts to parasites that subsequently infect the catfish. These parasites can cause nearly 100% mortality of a pond population in severe cases. Thus, it is important to understand the ecology of the macroinvertebrates and what roles they play in the produciton pond environment as to create better management strategies for catfish farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a small piece of a larger project aiming to investigation snail ecology, seasonal movement, and timing of parasitism. The subsection of the project hopes to fill a knowledge gap in the literature and understanding of the catfish production pond. A multitude of studies have investigated phytoplankton diversity and the effects of different groups on the production cycle; however, little information exists on the macroinvertebrate community and how these species may alter, facilitate, or antagonize processes within the pond that may be important to production. A better understanding of the macroinvertebrate diversity and their functions could provide new insights and management strategies that utilize natural pond ecology to improve catfish production.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) and occupancy models to estimate atypical Aeromonas hydrophila (aAh) prevalence in catfish</title>
      <link>/publication/aeromonas-swabs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/aeromonas-swabs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Worry, I&#39;m a Doctor!</title>
      <link>/post/2020/2020-04-21-doctoral-defense/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020/2020-04-21-doctoral-defense/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, April 20, 2020, I successfully defended my doctoral research! In the midst of the COVID-19 lockdown, the defense was completely virtual (other than one of my co-advisors being in the room). Other than a couple of small audio issues, everything went swimmingly! (Get it?! fish….swimmingly…..ok, you get it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation lasted right at an hour with a some great questions coming from those that attended. Immediately after the presentation my committee and I sat down for the virtual closed-door session. There were a few butterflies at the start but after a couple of questions I regained my confidence and coasted through most of the session. We discussed a few things we wanted to improve on the dissertation but, overall, the committee was very happy with where we were at and what we had accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020/images/thesis-defense-cartoon.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biocontrol of Proliferative Gill Disease using Gambusia</title>
      <link>/project/pgd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pgd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Proliferative Gill Disease (PGD) is a prominant disease concern in catfish aquaculture of the southeastern United States and is the third leading disease found in the Delta region of Mississippi. In an effort to mitigate the effects of PGD, we have evaluated the efficacy of stocking &lt;em&gt;Gambusia&lt;/em&gt; spp. at various densities to serve as a dead-end host for the &lt;em&gt;Henneguya ictaluri&lt;/em&gt; parasite. Previous research has shown that fish mucous from multiple species can activate attachment of the parasite, even if the fish is not a viable host.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphometric Analysis of Trematode Parasites</title>
      <link>/project/trematodes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/trematodes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Identification of parasite taxa can be difficult and is often based on a limited number of specimens. A combination of morphology, life cycle host(s), distribution, and/or genetics are often used to classify novel species. Our research is using morphometric analysis to confirm taxon identification within the &lt;em&gt;Apharyngostrigea&lt;/em&gt; genus as well as develop specific morphometrics that can be used to rapidly differentiate among species.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Shenanigans</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-08-20-summer-shenanigans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-08-20-summer-shenanigans/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;So, my final summer as a PhD student just wrapped up and I have to say I’m pretty happy with how it turned out. This summer led to a wide range of new experiences, projects, and results. I have begun a collaboration with a parasitologist in the Mississippi State vet school, investigating trematode morphometrics for species identification. The parasitologist believes he has found several specimens that have been mis-identified, which has led to an artificial reduction in the diversity of this parasite genus. So, we are teaming up for a project using morphometrics and molecular data to determine the true identifications and (hopefully) update the key for this genus. After seeing the potential in this morphometric method, he has also mentioned looking at the morphometrics of some other organisms he has, so there will be much more to come on this topic in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Semester Wrap-up!</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-05-09-spring-update-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-05-09-spring-update-video/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As the spring semester wraps up and the 2018-19 school year comes to a close. I am currently prepping for the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;LAST&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; field season of my doctoral work! I am slated to graduate in May 2020, which means I will be defending my dissertation in February or March, most likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to create a quick video, just so you all could get an idea of where we are with our systems model for the &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; pathogen. The model is built within a free, online app called &lt;a href=&#34;https://insightmaker.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Maker&lt;/a&gt;, if you follow the link and click on “Explore Insights”, then search “Aeromonas” you will see a few different models that I have built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular model has gone through many, many iterations thusfar and will continue to change as we move forward and gain new information. However, we feel we are really starting to hone the model and the dynamics seem to be working in a reasonable fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, below is a short (~5 min) video explaining some of the basics of our model and a couple of example scenarios to show the the pathogen and, more importantly, how a farmer handles the pathogen may effect their financial outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;/post/2019/files/Richardson_Spring 2019 Update Video.mp4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for Prelims!</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-01-23-prelim-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-01-23-prelim-prep/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, the time has officially arrived! Next week, I will begin my preliminary exams to fulfill my requirements to move from a Ph.D student to a Ph.D candidate! This means that starting on Monday, &lt;strong&gt;I will start a week of written exams&lt;/strong&gt;, one from each of my dissertation committee members.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 2 months or so, I have been studying every aspect of biology, ecology, immunology, and aquaculture that relates to my research. On Monday, I will receive the first of 5 written exams. Each day, one of my committee members will provide me with exam questions of their choosing. &lt;strong&gt;Any information that a biologist working in the fields of aquaculture, biology, and/or immunology would be expected to know is fair game!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have 24 hours to complete each set of exam questions, then the next set will be provided and I will continue this process until I have completed an exam for each member. The set-up for preliminary exams is different for each student/committee, but my committee has decided on the following rules: **&lt;em&gt;1)** I will receive an exam each day and have 24 hours to complete it; &lt;strong&gt;2)&lt;/strong&gt; I can use any materials that I have in hard copy or that are present on my computer; &lt;strong&gt;3)&lt;/strong&gt; I am not allowed to access the internet to answer any questions.&lt;/em&gt; I, personally, enjoy this set up because it allows my committee to ask more in-depth/rigorous questions and forces me to use the information I already know to synthesize the foundation of my answer. However, I still have the option to use other texts to bolster my answers and provide additional support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I have completed my written exams, my committee and I will meet on Feb. 14th to conduct the oral exam. &lt;strong&gt;The oral exam will likely last 2-4 hours&lt;/strong&gt; and during that time the committee members have the chance to test my knowlege on any new material that they did not ask during their written exam, or ask me to provide more detail/clarification about an answer from the written responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming I pass my exams, I will be admitted to Ph.D Candidate and I will be one step closer to being the first person in my family to complete a doctoral degree and reaching my goal of being a college professor! My expected graduation date is May 2020, so I am inching ever-closer to that point!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone that has supported me along this journey, and wish me luck! Hopefully, I will be able to post some good news in the near future!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haplotype Shuffle</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the project description of my &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas&lt;/em&gt; work, we are currently working with two different strains/genotypes of virulent &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt;. Dealing with multiple strains of a bacteria can prove difficult with creating vaccines or administering antibiotics so we wanted to see how the temporal distribution of these two strains compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we analyzed the isolates from various cases using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and electrophoresis. The image below shows what a typical electrophoresis gel looks like and how to read it. Each white band is a specific disease case and the location of each band tells us what strain of bacteria was collected from a specific case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/electrophoresis-gel.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using isolates collected from diseased catfish in the Mississippi Delta from 2013 (a year before the S14 strain was collected) to 2017, a very interesting pattern emerged. In less than 5 years, the new S14 strain made up 100% of all virulent Aeromonas cases (see figure below)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/temporal-shift.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, this could have important implications for people working to create a vaccine or administering antibiotics because there is no guarantee that the medications will work on both strains!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atypical Aeromonas hydrophila in Catfish</title>
      <link>/project/aeromonas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/aeromonas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Commercial aquaculture is a global, multibillion dollar industry in a constant battle about disease and pathogens. Commercial catfish production has been fighting an atypical strain of the bacterium, &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; (aAh), in the southeastern United States since the late 2000s. Atypical &lt;em&gt;A. hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; outbreaks range from chronic to acute and can cause losses totaling 10,000+ kg in only a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disease ecology and outbreak risk factors are poorly understood. Potential predictor variables have included phytoplankton blooms, nitrogenous waste build-up, water temperatures, and many others. However, the high variability in water quality and plankton communities and densities of earthen aquaculture ponds makes prediction of outbreaks more difficult and no study, to date, has been able to consistently predict vAh outbreaks within aquaculture ponds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to investigate vAh prevalence and risk factors associated with acute outbreaks in commercial catfish ponds. The project will examine the new strain of &lt;em&gt;A. hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; from a bacterium, better profiling the isolates collected from sick fish at two fish health diagnostic labs. An emphasis of this project is understanding the dynamics of the catfish aquaculture pond. Knowledge accrued from an overall systems model can then be used to inform decisions and variables used in an epidemiology model. By focusing on the environment as well as the pathogen and host, the study moves toward true eco-epidemiology and provides a better overall understanding of the emerging pathogen and its ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
