<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Worry, I&#39;m a Doctor!</title>
      <link>/post/2020/2020-04-21-doctoral-defense/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020/2020-04-21-doctoral-defense/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, April 20, 2020, I successfully defended my doctoral research! In the midst of the COVID-19 lockdown, the defense was completely virtual (other than one of my co-advisors being in the room). Other than a couple of small audio issues, everything went swimmingly! (Get it?! fish….swimmingly…..ok, you get it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation lasted right at an hour with a some great questions coming from those that attended. Immediately after the presentation my committee and I sat down for the virtual closed-door session. There were a few butterflies at the start but after a couple of questions I regained my confidence and coasted through most of the session. We discussed a few things we wanted to improve on the dissertation but, overall, the committee was very happy with where we were at and what we had accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020/images/thesis-defense-cartoon.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Shenanigans</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-08-20-summer-shenanigans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-08-20-summer-shenanigans/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;So, my final summer as a PhD student just wrapped up and I have to say I’m pretty happy with how it turned out. This summer led to a wide range of new experiences, projects, and results. I have begun a collaboration with a parasitologist in the Mississippi State vet school, investigating trematode morphometrics for species identification. The parasitologist believes he has found several specimens that have been mis-identified, which has led to an artificial reduction in the diversity of this parasite genus. So, we are teaming up for a project using morphometrics and molecular data to determine the true identifications and (hopefully) update the key for this genus. After seeing the potential in this morphometric method, he has also mentioned looking at the morphometrics of some other organisms he has, so there will be much more to come on this topic in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Semester Wrap-up!</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-05-09-spring-update-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-05-09-spring-update-video/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As the spring semester wraps up and the 2018-19 school year comes to a close. I am currently prepping for the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;LAST&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; field season of my doctoral work! I am slated to graduate in May 2020, which means I will be defending my dissertation in February or March, most likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to create a quick video, just so you all could get an idea of where we are with our systems model for the &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; pathogen. The model is built within a free, online app called &lt;a href=&#34;https://insightmaker.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Maker&lt;/a&gt;, if you follow the link and click on “Explore Insights”, then search “Aeromonas” you will see a few different models that I have built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular model has gone through many, many iterations thusfar and will continue to change as we move forward and gain new information. However, we feel we are really starting to hone the model and the dynamics seem to be working in a reasonable fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, below is a short (~5 min) video explaining some of the basics of our model and a couple of example scenarios to show the the pathogen and, more importantly, how a farmer handles the pathogen may effect their financial outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;/post/2019/files/Richardson_Spring 2019 Update Video.mp4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catalpa Creek Tributaries - A Preliminary Investigation</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-04-23-prelim-macroinvert-cca/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-04-23-prelim-macroinvert-cca/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;You can download a PDF copy of a recent presentation on the topic of this post &lt;a href=&#34;/post/2019/files/Richardson_Bradley_SWCS.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we have completed the lab work-up of nearly all of the 2018 macroinvertebrate coarse samples from the two Catalpa Creek tributaries that we are investigating. I have been working through some preliminary analyses to get an idea of what if going on the two streams. So far, the analyses include simple community indices including species richness, diversity, and evenness, and a Canonical Correlation Analysis (“CCA”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The community structure indices give us a glimpse of what the macroinvertebrate communities in these two streams look like overall. For instance, &lt;strong&gt;species richness&lt;/strong&gt; tells us how many different speices were collected from each stream. &lt;strong&gt;Species diversity&lt;/strong&gt; (Shannon Diversity, &lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;) provides information on how the proportions of individuals from each species compare to the total number of individuals collected. And, finally, &lt;strong&gt;evenness&lt;/strong&gt; (Shannon Evenness, &lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;) gives us information on whether the each species has approximately the same number of individuals, or if there are rare and/or dominant species that are accounting for most of the abundances in the samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What our data shows, so far, is that the total number of individuals collected is actually higher in our impacted (“degraded”) stream than our reference (“healthy”) stream by nearly 30%; however, the reference stream has a higher species richness, diversity, and evenness! So, this hints that although we have collected more individuals from the impacted stream, the reference stream is actually more stable and may provide a wider breadth of quality habitats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/macroinvert-sample.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, community structure indices are great, but they can’t give us the whole story. This is where the CCA that I mentioned above comes in! Canonical Correlation Analysis allows us to tie species abundances from our macroinvertebrate samples to the stream characteristics that we have measured! This can help us start to tease out what stream characteristics may be leading to that increase in richness, diversity, and evenness within the reference stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a graphical representation of our CCA. The way this works is that arrows represent the stream characteristics that we have looked at so far. The direction of the arrow indicates an increase in that specific characteristic. So, for instance, because the &lt;em&gt;Sand&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gravel&lt;/em&gt; arrows are pointing in opposite directions, this means that areas with more sand, usually have less gravel, and vice versa - makes sense right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/macroinvert-cca-april2019.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The black (impacted) and red (reference) dots represent individual sample sites within the two streams we are working on. The placement of those dots in relation to the arrows indicates the major stream characteristics of each site. For example, a cluster of 5 red dots are located near the end of the &lt;em&gt;Leafpack&lt;/em&gt; arrow, which indicates that the presence of leafpacks at these sites are what sets them apart the most from the other sites we have sampled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the blue names represent the different macroinvertebrate taxa that we are interested in. Their locations, similar to the sites we just discussed, provide information on the stream characteristic that best explains their abundance. So, if we look at the cluster of &lt;em&gt;Crayfish&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Caddisfly&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Mayfly&lt;/em&gt;, these three group fairly closly to the &lt;em&gt;Gravel&lt;/em&gt; arrow which indicates that higher abundances of these three taxa are usually associated with higher amounts of gravel. This makes sense, particularly for caddisflies and mayflies because they are sensitive to changes in water quality and can often be found in riffle habitats, which are usually dominated by gravel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a snapshot of what was happening within the streams for the fall of 2018, we can continue to work through the “fine” samples and begin work on the 2019 samples. As we continue to build our dataset, we hope to eventually determine some ways that we can help to restore our impacted stream and bring back some of that biodiversity. This impacted stream is slated to be transformed into a wetland education area, so we are hopeful that we can provide those in charge in important information about the stream health before, during, and after construction of this wetland.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for Prelims!</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-01-23-prelim-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-01-23-prelim-prep/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, the time has officially arrived! Next week, I will begin my preliminary exams to fulfill my requirements to move from a Ph.D student to a Ph.D candidate! This means that starting on Monday, &lt;strong&gt;I will start a week of written exams&lt;/strong&gt;, one from each of my dissertation committee members.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 2 months or so, I have been studying every aspect of biology, ecology, immunology, and aquaculture that relates to my research. On Monday, I will receive the first of 5 written exams. Each day, one of my committee members will provide me with exam questions of their choosing. &lt;strong&gt;Any information that a biologist working in the fields of aquaculture, biology, and/or immunology would be expected to know is fair game!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have 24 hours to complete each set of exam questions, then the next set will be provided and I will continue this process until I have completed an exam for each member. The set-up for preliminary exams is different for each student/committee, but my committee has decided on the following rules: **&lt;em&gt;1)** I will receive an exam each day and have 24 hours to complete it; &lt;strong&gt;2)&lt;/strong&gt; I can use any materials that I have in hard copy or that are present on my computer; &lt;strong&gt;3)&lt;/strong&gt; I am not allowed to access the internet to answer any questions.&lt;/em&gt; I, personally, enjoy this set up because it allows my committee to ask more in-depth/rigorous questions and forces me to use the information I already know to synthesize the foundation of my answer. However, I still have the option to use other texts to bolster my answers and provide additional support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I have completed my written exams, my committee and I will meet on Feb. 14th to conduct the oral exam. &lt;strong&gt;The oral exam will likely last 2-4 hours&lt;/strong&gt; and during that time the committee members have the chance to test my knowlege on any new material that they did not ask during their written exam, or ask me to provide more detail/clarification about an answer from the written responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming I pass my exams, I will be admitted to Ph.D Candidate and I will be one step closer to being the first person in my family to complete a doctoral degree and reaching my goal of being a college professor! My expected graduation date is May 2020, so I am inching ever-closer to that point!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone that has supported me along this journey, and wish me luck! Hopefully, I will be able to post some good news in the near future!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haplotype Shuffle</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the project description of my &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas&lt;/em&gt; work, we are currently working with two different strains/genotypes of virulent &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt;. Dealing with multiple strains of a bacteria can prove difficult with creating vaccines or administering antibiotics so we wanted to see how the temporal distribution of these two strains compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we analyzed the isolates from various cases using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and electrophoresis. The image below shows what a typical electrophoresis gel looks like and how to read it. Each white band is a specific disease case and the location of each band tells us what strain of bacteria was collected from a specific case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/electrophoresis-gel.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using isolates collected from diseased catfish in the Mississippi Delta from 2013 (a year before the S14 strain was collected) to 2017, a very interesting pattern emerged. In less than 5 years, the new S14 strain made up 100% of all virulent Aeromonas cases (see figure below)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/temporal-shift.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, this could have important implications for people working to create a vaccine or administering antibiotics because there is no guarantee that the medications will work on both strains!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pens to Fight Fears</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-12-07-pens-fight-fears/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-12-07-pens-fight-fears/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stop teaching students that they need to remove or hide all of their mistakes! This instills a fear of making mistakes that will also reduce the student’s willingness to try new things!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words and stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/penchild.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment and let me know how you feel about this idea of moving to pens and saving pencils for special occasions, or if you agree/disagree with my view of the situation. I’d love to start a conversation on this type of thing because that is the only way we will ever make progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Should Go Outside More</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-30-outdoor-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-30-outdoor-ed/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe we should teach topics about nature…mixed with a little nature?! Go outside! Get muddy, scrape a knee, step in a puddle, pull a leaf off of a tree (sparingly, of course)! These experiences are crucial to building connections between theory and reality!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days it seems more and more time is spent indoors, and I feel that there is one place that can help mitigate that issue - the classroom. If students are going to learn about the natural world and plants and critters, then they need to also &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; these things in a meaningful way! I know, I know, the amount of “teaching to the test” and time limits that burden primary and secondary teachers these days probably make it feel like this is an impossible feat, but I promise you it can be done! And it has remarkable potential to help foster growth in the students as well as the teachers! Students that are exposed to nature in a constructive and educational way on a regular basis have shown increases in a variety of academic measures, including core subject scores (math, science, and reading), school attendance, and overall GPA (SEER 2000). And some studies even suggest that cognitive skills are better honed outdoors than in a classroom (Eaton 2000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classroom lessons often portray a very static world, with much of the information provided in a dogma-esc fashion rather than a general framework. These types of lessons and “cookie-cutter” experiments can lead to a boring view of science and push students away before they get the chance to experience the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;wonder and unknown of true experimentation and data collection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Learning outdoors not only helps students to make connections within the lessons, it also makes for a more memorable experience. Several studies, including Dierking and Falk (2007), have found that people can recall outdoor studies and fieldwork from their schooling for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/outdoored.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it is important to note that just going outdoors all willy-nilly is not necessarily constructive. Outdoor education projects/lessons require adequate planning and effort on the front-end. For instance, an outdoor lesson may be used to explore differences in bug morphology, but there should also be a follow-up lesson that helps students to understand the importance of the morphology in a meaningful way. Maybe the shape helps them hide from predators, maybe the shape of their legs helps them jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, an effort should be made to have students use this new knowledge to expand their thinking, this could be done with an imagination exercise where the instructor describes an imaginary habitat and students have to design their own bugs and explain how each feature helps them survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to realize here is that although the science classroom seems like the logical choice for outdoor education, the idea can be expanded to any subject. One of the most powerful messages I’ve ever come across was from an art class that worked on a collective project about the litter and pollution around their school. Each student used their own choice of medium to show the impact humans are having on their immediate environment; some students used a camera, some used sketches or paints. But the collective message was very powerful and attention grabbing. Through the project students not only connected with their local environment, but also became environmentally conscious about their decision-making. They were able to draw a link between the topics taught in their biology courses and the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many students may have trouble seeing the importance of art in the world of science, and though there are many important reasons to mesh the two, my particular favorite is the need for creativity! Ask anyone in a science-related field and they will tell you that you have to &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;find ways to solve problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and these fixes can become pretty creative. Maybe the equipment you need to carry out a particular research project doesn’t exist…well, now you have to design and create the equipment you need - you better bet creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment and let me know of any outdoor education experiences you have had, or any that you use in your curricula. Also, if you are looking for more ways to move the teaching outdoors but struggling to come up with ideas, let me know and we can try to brainstorm together to come up with something new for you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Learn Little From Bubbles</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-23-bubbles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-23-bubbles/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;As you move through the seemingly endless pile of tests, wielding the red pen of fury and striking through wrong answer after wrong answer. Students are consistently marking the incorrect answer on the multiple choice section, but reading the question you see no issues. This may be hinting toward a larger issue in the students’ understanding, but you can’t tell because you left them nothing but a bubble to fill in…this is a disservice to both you and your students.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the tests given at the secondary and post-secondary level reward students that are good test takers while never really testing the knowledge and understanding of the subject. Multiple choice, true/false, and matching formatted questions test a student’s ability to recall isolated pieces of information from previous lessons; however, there is little to no test of their ability to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that information. These questions also fail to encourage broad-scope thinking or “looking at the big picture”, these events are isolated and may possess little meaning by themselves. &lt;strong&gt;Tests should aim to test the level of understanding&lt;/strong&gt; rather than memorization, though memorization may be an important piece of this understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple choice and true/false questions are a wonderful way to assess student knowledge in a snap. However, they are limited in the information they can provide an instructor when the student answers incorrectly. There are a range of reason that the student may have selected the wrong answer, including misunderstanding information in the lesson, misreading the question, accidentally circling the wrong answer, or maybe they really don’t know the answer. If you have only provided a multiple choice question you, as an instructor, are unable to determine the root of the issue and fix it. Sure, you might be able to ask the student(s) at the next class period but that might be a few days away and the students may not remember why they selected that answer, or you may just not have time to discuss the issue due to time constraints. In this case, you and your students are all left wondering what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not saying that you should stop including multiple-choice questions in your tests and/or quizzes, I’m just saying that there should be &lt;strong&gt;some other follow-up question that allows the student to justify their answer or explain their choice&lt;/strong&gt;. This simple addition can accomplish several things. First, it will make the student really &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about the answer and draw on past information rather than possibly just recalling a word they memorized. It will also provide the instructor with how well the student(s) understand the concept. Are they justifying the answer with the correct information and making the right connections between topics? Or are they displaying a misconception in a principle that is skewing their thinking? If there is a common misconception showing up among several students then the topic should certainly be retaught and/or discussed in the following class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I challenge you to look at previous (or even upcoming) tests and see if you’re testing information recall or subject understanding. You may notice that many parts of the test are not aligned with the goals of your unit/lesson cirriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, comment below if you have any other ideas on how to test students for understanding and mastery, rather than memorization and isolated information recall. I have touched on only &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;one of many&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ways to improve testing and assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Note-taking Is Not One-Size-Fits-All</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;We’ve all been there, you open your notes from class and there it is: a long, outline-form narrative of black ink. Somehow you have to convince your mind to wade through this jungle of bullet points and determine what information is important and should be retained. Eventually your brain just gives up and you suddenly become very interested in the informercial on tv.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have some pity on your brain, or your students’ brains. The human brain is a wonderfully complex and powerful piece of machinary! It is able to distill images from randomly placed, overlapping objects, discern colors, formulate (relatively) complex mental models for how things works…and you are providing it with a myriad of black ink and shorthand sentences. Is it any wonder why you can’t focus or remember what you studied? No! You’re brain &lt;strong&gt;needs something to grab its attention and tell it “this is important”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking is an important skill for students, teachers, and those employed in nearly every facet of the workforce. Students are urged to take notes in the classroom and several studies have shown that students that create their own notes show increased information retention (i.e. Katayama and Crooks 2001). The problem is that many students struggle to stay engaged and take notes throughout the entire class period. Like the story above, the brain loses interest in the monotony of writing down lecture notes…in a linear format…in black/blue ink…in straight lines…in all text. The brain &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; activity to keep it engaged and focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/9amLecture.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking strategies are primarily divided into 2 categories: linear and nonlinear. Linear strategies are the most common style and appears to be the trend all across the globe (Buzan and Buzan 1993, Piolat 2001). I would guess that most students latch onto linear format notes (usually outline format) because it is really the only shorthand method of taking down information they were formally exposed to during their education. Think back to your first writing/grammar class and the first paper you had to write, how did the teacher have you organize your paper? Most likely, it was an outline. Now, the outline format works wonderfully for this instance and is a very powerful tool; however, that doesn’t mean it should be used in every situation. And, in practice, can actually have a negative impact on information retention when used for many notetaking situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this is often the only type of shorthand information drafting that students are exposed to and puts many students at a disadvantage. Not all students think in a linear, rigid manner; many are nonlinear thinkers and do no perform well when given monotonous lines of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to level the playing field and boost engagement, students should also be exposed to the wide variety of nonlinear notetaking methods! Nonlinearity is how the brain functions by default; thus, these methods are often very useful and easy for students to grasp. These nonlinear strategies utilize multiple colors, pictures, lines directly linking information, and keywords rather than strings of text (see Farrand et al. 2002)! Several studies (e.g. Beel 2009, D’Antoni 2010, Edwards and Cooper 2010, Pauk and Owens 2011, and many others) have investigated their usefulness in a wide array of scenarios and the positive feedback continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal favorite form of nonlinear notetaking is &lt;a href=&#34;www.mindmapping.com&#34;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;. Mind Maps begin with the central idea in the middle of the page and key information radiating out in all directions. Each radiating arm is then radiated further with increasely detailed information. The Mind Map can be as simple or elaborate as you choose and, best of all, &lt;strong&gt;it’s completely scaleable!&lt;/strong&gt; Each Mind Map from a given lesson can be envisioned as one radiating arm branching out from the central idea/topic of the class!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/MindMap.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind Maps are incredible assests for not only students, but teachers as well! I have used this strategy extensively in both my schooling and teaching settings. By continuosly changing colors and adding quick sketches to help explain the idea, students remain engaged in the classroom and can see direct links between information and how they fit together. This also achieves another goal, moving away from powerpoint slides. The plague of powerpoint slide presentations for instruction is a continuing issue in teh classroom, primarily at the college level. However, by using Mind Maps, or any other nonlinear form of notetaking, the teacher can build the notes &lt;strong&gt;along with the student&lt;/strong&gt; and help to avoid confusion of how information fits together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outline-form and other linear formats of notetaking have their place and uses (recipes, mapping out a paper, etc.); however, if the topic you are learning, or teaching, is not a linear construct then there is no reason to force linear notes to tell the story and provide the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as you move through your studies, or your career, consider exploring a new form of notetaking. Your brain will thank you and chances are you will be much more alert and engaged in the topic; you will likely also recall more of the information when/if it is needed later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
