<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>disease | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/disease/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/disease/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>disease</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>disease</title>
      <link>/tag/disease/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity in catfish production ponds</title>
      <link>/project/pond-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pond-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Approximately 50% of U.S.-raised catfish production takes place in the state of Mississippi. Catfish production occurs in earthen ponds where many natural processes still occur. With this production setup, natural pond inhabitants must be included in the understanding of the pond environment and how their presence, behaviors, and ecology effect the production of catfish. Many macroinvertebrates can be nuisance species at various periods within the production cycle. For instance, dragonfly nymphs can heavily predate on catfish fry after stocking of ponds for fingerling production. Meanwhile, other macroinvertebrates serve as intermediate hosts to parasites that subsequently infect the catfish. These parasites can cause nearly 100% mortality of a pond population in severe cases. Thus, it is important to understand the ecology of the macroinvertebrates and what roles they play in the produciton pond environment as to create better management strategies for catfish farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a small piece of a larger project aiming to investigation snail ecology, seasonal movement, and timing of parasitism. The subsection of the project hopes to fill a knowledge gap in the literature and understanding of the catfish production pond. A multitude of studies have investigated phytoplankton diversity and the effects of different groups on the production cycle; however, little information exists on the macroinvertebrate community and how these species may alter, facilitate, or antagonize processes within the pond that may be important to production. A better understanding of the macroinvertebrate diversity and their functions could provide new insights and management strategies that utilize natural pond ecology to improve catfish production.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphometric Analysis of Trematode Parasites</title>
      <link>/project/trematode-morphometrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/trematode-morphometrics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Identification of parasite taxa can be difficult and is often based on a limited number of specimens. A combination of morphology, life cycle host(s), distribution, and/or genetics are often used to classify novel species. Our research is using morphometric analysis to confirm taxon identification within the &lt;em&gt;Apharyngostrigea&lt;/em&gt; genus as well as develop specific morphometrics that can be used to rapidly differentiate among species.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atypical Aeromonas hydrophila in Catfish</title>
      <link>/project/aeromonas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/aeromonas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Commercial aquaculture is a global, multibillion dollar industry in a constant battle about disease and pathogens. Commercial catfish production has been fighting an atypical strain of the bacterium, &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; (aAh), in the southeastern United States since the late 2000s. Atypical &lt;em&gt;A. hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; outbreaks range from chronic to acute and can cause losses totaling 10,000+ kg in only a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disease ecology and outbreak risk factors are poorly understood. Potential predictor variables have included phytoplankton blooms, nitrogenous waste build-up, water temperatures, and many others. However, the high variability in water quality and plankton communities and densities of earthen aquaculture ponds makes prediction of outbreaks more difficult and no study, to date, has been able to consistently predict vAh outbreaks within aquaculture ponds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to investigate vAh prevalence and risk factors associated with acute outbreaks in commercial catfish ponds. The project will examine the new strain of &lt;em&gt;A. hydrophila&lt;/em&gt; from a bacterium, better profiling the isolates collected from sick fish at two fish health diagnostic labs. An emphasis of this project is understanding the dynamics of the catfish aquaculture pond. Knowledge accrued from an overall systems model can then be used to inform decisions and variables used in an epidemiology model. By focusing on the environment as well as the pathogen and host, the study moves toward true eco-epidemiology and provides a better overall understanding of the emerging pathogen and its ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
