<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>macroinvertebrates | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/macroinvertebrates/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/macroinvertebrates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>macroinvertebrates</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>macroinvertebrates</title>
      <link>/tag/macroinvertebrates/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catalpa Creek Tributaries - A Preliminary Investigation</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-04-23-prelim-macroinvert-cca/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-04-23-prelim-macroinvert-cca/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;You can download a PDF copy of a recent presentation on the topic of this post &lt;a href=&#34;/post/2019/files/Richardson_Bradley_SWCS.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we have completed the lab work-up of nearly all of the 2018 macroinvertebrate coarse samples from the two Catalpa Creek tributaries that we are investigating. I have been working through some preliminary analyses to get an idea of what if going on the two streams. So far, the analyses include simple community indices including species richness, diversity, and evenness, and a Canonical Correlation Analysis (“CCA”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The community structure indices give us a glimpse of what the macroinvertebrate communities in these two streams look like overall. For instance, &lt;strong&gt;species richness&lt;/strong&gt; tells us how many different speices were collected from each stream. &lt;strong&gt;Species diversity&lt;/strong&gt; (Shannon Diversity, &lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;) provides information on how the proportions of individuals from each species compare to the total number of individuals collected. And, finally, &lt;strong&gt;evenness&lt;/strong&gt; (Shannon Evenness, &lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;) gives us information on whether the each species has approximately the same number of individuals, or if there are rare and/or dominant species that are accounting for most of the abundances in the samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What our data shows, so far, is that the total number of individuals collected is actually higher in our impacted (“degraded”) stream than our reference (“healthy”) stream by nearly 30%; however, the reference stream has a higher species richness, diversity, and evenness! So, this hints that although we have collected more individuals from the impacted stream, the reference stream is actually more stable and may provide a wider breadth of quality habitats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/macroinvert-sample.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, community structure indices are great, but they can’t give us the whole story. This is where the CCA that I mentioned above comes in! Canonical Correlation Analysis allows us to tie species abundances from our macroinvertebrate samples to the stream characteristics that we have measured! This can help us start to tease out what stream characteristics may be leading to that increase in richness, diversity, and evenness within the reference stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a graphical representation of our CCA. The way this works is that arrows represent the stream characteristics that we have looked at so far. The direction of the arrow indicates an increase in that specific characteristic. So, for instance, because the &lt;em&gt;Sand&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gravel&lt;/em&gt; arrows are pointing in opposite directions, this means that areas with more sand, usually have less gravel, and vice versa - makes sense right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/macroinvert-cca-april2019.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The black (impacted) and red (reference) dots represent individual sample sites within the two streams we are working on. The placement of those dots in relation to the arrows indicates the major stream characteristics of each site. For example, a cluster of 5 red dots are located near the end of the &lt;em&gt;Leafpack&lt;/em&gt; arrow, which indicates that the presence of leafpacks at these sites are what sets them apart the most from the other sites we have sampled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the blue names represent the different macroinvertebrate taxa that we are interested in. Their locations, similar to the sites we just discussed, provide information on the stream characteristic that best explains their abundance. So, if we look at the cluster of &lt;em&gt;Crayfish&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Caddisfly&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Mayfly&lt;/em&gt;, these three group fairly closly to the &lt;em&gt;Gravel&lt;/em&gt; arrow which indicates that higher abundances of these three taxa are usually associated with higher amounts of gravel. This makes sense, particularly for caddisflies and mayflies because they are sensitive to changes in water quality and can often be found in riffle habitats, which are usually dominated by gravel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a snapshot of what was happening within the streams for the fall of 2018, we can continue to work through the “fine” samples and begin work on the 2019 samples. As we continue to build our dataset, we hope to eventually determine some ways that we can help to restore our impacted stream and bring back some of that biodiversity. This impacted stream is slated to be transformed into a wetland education area, so we are hopeful that we can provide those in charge in important information about the stream health before, during, and after construction of this wetland.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catalpa/Red Bud Creek</title>
      <link>/project/catalpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/catalpa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Catalpa/Red Bud Creek is a small stream that flows through the Mississippi State University campus, past the MSU Veterinary School facility, several agricultural research pastures, and the aquaculture research facility before ultimately draining into Tibbee Creek, which serves as a tributary to the Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway. The section of Catalpa Creek that flows past the MSU Veterinary School is prone to high flows and flash floods during heavy rain events. The stream can also receive high volumes of impervious surface run-off and drain overflows from the vet school facility. These disturbance events and the potential for point- and non-point-source contaminants raises many concerns when discussing the health of the stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a collaboration between members of the MSU Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (CCE) and myself to investigate the health of Catalpa Creek and evaluate any mitigation needs. My role in this collaboration is, primarily, to serve as the expert in stream ecology and aquatic macroinvertebrates. We are using standard methods to sample and evaluate macroinvertebrate communities to help assess stream health. In addition to macroinvertebrate sampling, members of the MSU CEE are monitoring water quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been a joint effort from faculty, research associates, graduate and undergraduate students, and volunteers. The ultimate goal of this project is to maintain and/or restore the integrity of Catalpa Creek and create a wetland education center in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in this project, you can find more information from one of the collaborators 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gri.msstate.edu/publications/docs/2016/06/14490Paper_SIU_XIX_Catalpa_Creek_Watershed_Planning.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magby Creek Outreach</title>
      <link>/project/magby/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/magby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Magby Creek is a small stream that flows near the Columbus High School (Columbus, MS). The stream has been heavily channelized and managed in some parts; however, the portion of the stream that this project focuses on is relatively unaltered. Aside from commercial and residential architecture near by, the stream has wide meanders, a low gradient, a riparian buffer that is mostly intact, and a good mix of gravel, sand, and silt substrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Ms. Pounders, a biology teacher at Columbus HS, was interested in building a long-term project that could provide her students (primarily under-represented, urban children) with real hands-on opportunities to apply the scientific knowledge they have learned in the classroom. She wanted something that could provide new experiences for the students and get them excited about biology, possibly showing them another avenue to college and/or a career. So Ms. Pounders and a small group of her students went to a water quality training workshop at the University of Maine to learn the techniques that they could apply to the small stream that flows near their school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was contacted by a mutual friend, who is also a Mississippi State University faculty member, to see if I would be willing to help with the project she had in mind. The project was originally going to include monitoring water quality of Magby Creek, including flow rate, dissolved oxygen, pH, and other parameters. During our first field day together, I mentioned also sampling aquatic macroinvertebrates and teaching the students how to use the Pollution Tolerance Index (PTI). This was another opportunity for the students to experience something they had likely never seen (or even thought about)&amp;hellip;AQAUTIC BUGS!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of this partnership, student ideas/projects have flourished! Most students use some piece of this research as their science fair projects while others help monitor the stream while focusing on other science topics for their projects. During our first year, the 5 students that worked on the project showed exceptional growth in confidence, critical thinking, and content information retention. In addition, they submitted three Science Fair projects; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;2 projects won 1st place in their respective categories&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and the five students earned &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;11 special recognition awards!!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
