<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>haplotype | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/haplotype/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/haplotype/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>haplotype</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>haplotype</title>
      <link>/tag/haplotype/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haplotype Shuffle</title>
      <link>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2019/2019-01-14-haplotype-shuffle/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the project description of my &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas&lt;/em&gt; work, we are currently working with two different strains/genotypes of virulent &lt;em&gt;Aeromonas hydrophila&lt;/em&gt;. Dealing with multiple strains of a bacteria can prove difficult with creating vaccines or administering antibiotics so we wanted to see how the temporal distribution of these two strains compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we analyzed the isolates from various cases using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and electrophoresis. The image below shows what a typical electrophoresis gel looks like and how to read it. Each white band is a specific disease case and the location of each band tells us what strain of bacteria was collected from a specific case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/electrophoresis-gel.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using isolates collected from diseased catfish in the Mississippi Delta from 2013 (a year before the S14 strain was collected) to 2017, a very interesting pattern emerged. In less than 5 years, the new S14 strain made up 100% of all virulent Aeromonas cases (see figure below)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019/images/temporal-shift.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, this could have important implications for people working to create a vaccine or administering antibiotics because there is no guarantee that the medications will work on both strains!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
