<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>classroom | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/classroom/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/classroom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>classroom</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>classroom</title>
      <link>/tag/classroom/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pens to Fight Fears</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-12-07-pens-fight-fears/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-12-07-pens-fight-fears/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stop teaching students that they need to remove or hide all of their mistakes! This instills a fear of making mistakes that will also reduce the student’s willingness to try new things!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draft - finish later&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/penchild.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment and let me know how you feel about this idea of moving to pens and saving pencils for special occasions, or if you agree/disagree with my view of the situation. I’d love to start a conversation on this type of thing because that is the only way we will ever make progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Learn Little From Bubbles</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-23-bubbles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-23-bubbles/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;As you move through the seemingly endless pile of tests, wielding the red pen of fury and striking through wrong answer after wrong answer. Students are consistently marking the incorrect answer on the multiple choice section, but reading the question you see no issues. This may be hinting toward a larger issue in the students’ understanding, but you can’t tell because you left them nothing but a bubble to fill in…this is a disservice to both you and your students.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the tests given at the secondary and post-secondary level reward students that are good test takers while never really testing the knowledge and understanding of the subject. Multiple choice, true/false, and matching formatted questions test a student’s ability to recall isolated pieces of information from previous lessons; however, there is little to no test of their ability to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that information. These questions also fail to encourage broad-scope thinking or “looking at the big picture”, these events are isolated and may possess little meaning by themselves. &lt;strong&gt;Tests should aim to test the level of understanding&lt;/strong&gt; rather than memorization, though memorization may be an important piece of this understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple choice and true/false questions are a wonderful way to assess student knowledge in a snap. However, they are limited in the information they can provide an instructor when the student answers incorrectly. There are a range of reason that the student may have selected the wrong answer, including misunderstanding information in the lesson, misreading the question, accidentally circling the wrong answer, or maybe they really don’t know the answer. If you have only provided a multiple choice question you, as an instructor, are unable to determine the root of the issue and fix it. Sure, you might be able to ask the student(s) at the next class period but that might be a few days away and the students may not remember why they selected that answer, or you may just not have time to discuss the issue due to time constraints. In this case, you and your students are all left wondering what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not saying that you should stop including multiple-choice questions in your tests and/or quizzes, I’m just saying that there should be &lt;strong&gt;some other follow-up question that allows the student to justify their answer or explain their choice&lt;/strong&gt;. This simple addition can accomplish several things. First, it will make the student really &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about the answer and draw on past information rather than possibly just recalling a word they memorized. It will also provide the instructor with how well the student(s) understand the concept. Are they justifying the answer with the correct information and making the right connections between topics? Or are they displaying a misconception in a principle that is skewing their thinking? If there is a common misconception showing up among several students then the topic should certainly be retaught and/or discussed in the following class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I challenge you to look at previous (or even upcoming) tests and see if you’re testing information recall or subject understanding. You may notice that many parts of the test are not aligned with the goals of your unit/lesson cirriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, comment below if you have any other ideas on how to test students for understanding and mastery, rather than memorization and isolated information recall. I have touched on only &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;one of many&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ways to improve testing and assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Note-taking Is Not One-Size-Fits-All</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;We’ve all been there, you open your notes from class and there it is: a long, outline-form narrative of black ink. Somehow you have to convince your mind to wade through this jungle of bullet points and determine what information is important and should be retained. Eventually your brain just gives up and you suddenly become very interested in the informercial on tv.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have some pity on your brain, or your students’ brains. The human brain is a wonderfully complex and powerful piece of machinary! It is able to distill images from randomly placed, overlapping objects, discern colors, formulate (relatively) complex mental models for how things works…and you are providing it with a myriad of black ink and shorthand sentences. Is it any wonder why you can’t focus or remember what you studied? No! You’re brain &lt;strong&gt;needs something to grab its attention and tell it “this is important”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking is an important skill for students, teachers, and those employed in nearly every facet of the workforce. Students are urged to take notes in the classroom and several studies have shown that students that create their own notes show increased information retention (i.e. Katayama and Crooks 2001). The problem is that many students struggle to stay engaged and take notes throughout the entire class period. Like the story above, the brain loses interest in the monotony of writing down lecture notes…in a linear format…in black/blue ink…in straight lines…in all text. The brain &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; activity to keep it engaged and focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/9amLecture.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking strategies are primarily divided into 2 categories: linear and nonlinear. Linear strategies are the most common style and appears to be the trend all across the globe (Buzan and Buzan 1993, Piolat 2001). I would guess that most students latch onto linear format notes (usually outline format) because it is really the only shorthand method of taking down information they were formally exposed to during their education. Think back to your first writing/grammar class and the first paper you had to write, how did the teacher have you organize your paper? Most likely, it was an outline. Now, the outline format works wonderfully for this instance and is a very powerful tool; however, that doesn’t mean it should be used in every situation. And, in practice, can actually have a negative impact on information retention when used for many notetaking situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this is often the only type of shorthand information drafting that students are exposed to and puts many students at a disadvantage. Not all students think in a linear, rigid manner; many are nonlinear thinkers and do no perform well when given monotonous lines of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to level the playing field and boost engagement, students should also be exposed to the wide variety of nonlinear notetaking methods! Nonlinearity is how the brain functions by default; thus, these methods are often very useful and easy for students to grasp. These nonlinear strategies utilize multiple colors, pictures, lines directly linking information, and keywords rather than strings of text (see Farrand et al. 2002)! Several studies (e.g. Beel 2009, D’Antoni 2010, Edwards and Cooper 2010, Pauk and Owens 2011, and many others) have investigated their usefulness in a wide array of scenarios and the positive feedback continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal favorite form of nonlinear notetaking is &lt;a href=&#34;www.mindmapping.com&#34;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;. Mind Maps begin with the central idea in the middle of the page and key information radiating out in all directions. Each radiating arm is then radiated further with increasely detailed information. The Mind Map can be as simple or elaborate as you choose and, best of all, &lt;strong&gt;it’s completely scaleable!&lt;/strong&gt; Each Mind Map from a given lesson can be envisioned as one radiating arm branching out from the central idea/topic of the class!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/MindMap.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind Maps are incredible assests for not only students, but teachers as well! I have used this strategy extensively in both my schooling and teaching settings. By continuosly changing colors and adding quick sketches to help explain the idea, students remain engaged in the classroom and can see direct links between information and how they fit together. This also achieves another goal, moving away from powerpoint slides. The plague of powerpoint slide presentations for instruction is a continuing issue in teh classroom, primarily at the college level. However, by using Mind Maps, or any other nonlinear form of notetaking, the teacher can build the notes &lt;strong&gt;along with the student&lt;/strong&gt; and help to avoid confusion of how information fits together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outline-form and other linear formats of notetaking have their place and uses (recipes, mapping out a paper, etc.); however, if the topic you are learning, or teaching, is not a linear construct then there is no reason to force linear notes to tell the story and provide the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as you move through your studies, or your career, consider exploring a new form of notetaking. Your brain will thank you and chances are you will be much more alert and engaged in the topic; you will likely also recall more of the information when/if it is needed later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
