<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>parasite | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/parasite/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/parasite/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>parasite</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>parasite</title>
      <link>/tag/parasite/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Trematode Risk Through Host Control</title>
      <link>/project/trematode-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/trematode-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trematode parasite outbreaks are are detrimental to the catfish aquaculture industry. &lt;em&gt;Bolbophorus damnificus&lt;/em&gt; is the most common trematode parasite encountered in southeastern US catfish production. The complex life cycle of &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; includes a snail (first intermediate host), catfish (second intermediate host), and the American White Pelican &lt;em&gt;Pelecanus erythrorhynchos&lt;/em&gt; (final/tertiary host). The American White Pelican is a federally-protected species, limiting the options for management, and there are currently no approved therapeutics for trematode infections in catfish. Thus, the snail is the most viable target of &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; management. &lt;em&gt;P. trivolvis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. havanensis&lt;/em&gt; are common cohabitants in catfish aquaculture ponds and each can serve as the snail host in the &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; life cycle. We are working to better understand snail populations in these ponds to better inform treatment and management plans. Additionally, we are investigating natural and chemical methods/regimens to safely control snail populations as a way of reducing &lt;em&gt;B. damnificus&lt;/em&gt; risk on catfish production facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biocontrol of Proliferative Gill Disease using Gambusia</title>
      <link>/project/pgd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pgd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Proliferative Gill Disease (PGD) is a prominant disease concern in catfish aquaculture of the southeastern United States and is the third leading disease found in the Delta region of Mississippi. In an effort to mitigate the effects of PGD, we have evaluated the efficacy of stocking &lt;em&gt;Gambusia&lt;/em&gt; spp. at various densities to serve as a dead-end host for the &lt;em&gt;Henneguya ictaluri&lt;/em&gt; parasite. Previous research has shown that fish mucous from multiple species can activate attachment of the parasite, even if the fish is not a viable host.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphometric Analysis of Trematode Parasites</title>
      <link>/project/trematode-morphometrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/trematode-morphometrics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Identification of parasite taxa can be difficult and is often based on a limited number of specimens. A combination of morphology, life cycle host(s), distribution, and/or genetics are often used to classify novel species. Our research is using morphometric analysis to confirm taxon identification within the &lt;em&gt;Apharyngostrigea&lt;/em&gt; genus as well as develop specific morphometrics that can be used to rapidly differentiate among species.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
