<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>education | Bradley M. Richardson</title>
    <link>/tag/education/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>education</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Bradley M Richardson</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>education</title>
      <link>/tag/education/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Should Go Outside More</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-30-outdoor-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-30-outdoor-ed/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe we should teach topics about nature…mixed with a little nature?! Go outside! Get muddy, scrape a knee, step in a puddle, pull a leaf off of a tree (sparingly, of course)! These experiences are crucial to building connections between theory and reality!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days it seems more and more time is spent indoors, and I feel that there is one place that can help mitigate that issue - the classroom. If students are going to learn about the natural world and plants and critters, then they need to also &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; these things in a meaningful way! I know, I know, the amount of “teaching to the test” and time limits that burden primary and secondary teachers these days probably make it feel like this is an impossible feat, but I promise you it can be done! And it has remarkable potential to help foster growth in the students as well as the teachers! Students that are exposed to nature in a constructive and educational way on a regular basis have shown increases in a variety of academic measures, including core subject scores (math, science, and reading), school attendance, and overall GPA (SEER 2000). And some studies even suggest that cognitive skills are better honed outdoors than in a classroom (Eaton 2000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classroom lessons often portray a very static world, with much of the information provided in a dogma-esc fashion rather than a general framework. These types of lessons and “cookie-cutter” experiments can lead to a boring view of science and push students away before they get the chance to experience the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;wonder and unknown of true experimentation and data collection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Learning outdoors not only helps students to make connections within the lessons, it also makes for a more memorable experience. Several studies, including Dierking and Falk (2007), have found that people can recall outdoor studies and fieldwork from their schooling for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/outdoored.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it is important to note that just going outdoors all willy-nilly is not necessarily constructive. Outdoor education projects/lessons require adequate planning and effort on the front-end. For instance, an outdoor lesson may be used to explore differences in bug morphology, but there should also be a follow-up lesson that helps students to understand the importance of the morphology in a meaningful way. Maybe the shape helps them hide from predators, maybe the shape of their legs helps them jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, an effort should be made to have students use this new knowledge to expand their thinking, this could be done with an imagination exercise where the instructor describes an imaginary habitat and students have to design their own bugs and explain how each feature helps them survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to realize here is that although the science classroom seems like the logical choice for outdoor education, the idea can be expanded to any subject. One of the most powerful messages I’ve ever come across was from an art class that worked on a collective project about the litter and pollution around their school. Each student used their own choice of medium to show the impact humans are having on their immediate environment; some students used a camera, some used sketches or paints. But the collective message was very powerful and attention grabbing. Through the project students not only connected with their local environment, but also became environmentally conscious about their decision-making. They were able to draw a link between the topics taught in their biology courses and the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many students may have trouble seeing the importance of art in the world of science, and though there are many important reasons to mesh the two, my particular favorite is the need for creativity! Ask anyone in a science-related field and they will tell you that you have to &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;find ways to solve problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and these fixes can become pretty creative. Maybe the equipment you need to carry out a particular research project doesn’t exist…well, now you have to design and create the equipment you need - you better bet creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please leave a comment and let me know of any outdoor education experiences you have had, or any that you use in your curricula. Also, if you are looking for more ways to move the teaching outdoors but struggling to come up with ideas, let me know and we can try to brainstorm together to come up with something new for you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Note-taking Is Not One-Size-Fits-All</title>
      <link>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2017/2017-11-16-note-taking/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;We’ve all been there, you open your notes from class and there it is: a long, outline-form narrative of black ink. Somehow you have to convince your mind to wade through this jungle of bullet points and determine what information is important and should be retained. Eventually your brain just gives up and you suddenly become very interested in the informercial on tv.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have some pity on your brain, or your students’ brains. The human brain is a wonderfully complex and powerful piece of machinary! It is able to distill images from randomly placed, overlapping objects, discern colors, formulate (relatively) complex mental models for how things works…and you are providing it with a myriad of black ink and shorthand sentences. Is it any wonder why you can’t focus or remember what you studied? No! You’re brain &lt;strong&gt;needs something to grab its attention and tell it “this is important”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking is an important skill for students, teachers, and those employed in nearly every facet of the workforce. Students are urged to take notes in the classroom and several studies have shown that students that create their own notes show increased information retention (i.e. Katayama and Crooks 2001). The problem is that many students struggle to stay engaged and take notes throughout the entire class period. Like the story above, the brain loses interest in the monotony of writing down lecture notes…in a linear format…in black/blue ink…in straight lines…in all text. The brain &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; activity to keep it engaged and focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/9amLecture.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notetaking strategies are primarily divided into 2 categories: linear and nonlinear. Linear strategies are the most common style and appears to be the trend all across the globe (Buzan and Buzan 1993, Piolat 2001). I would guess that most students latch onto linear format notes (usually outline format) because it is really the only shorthand method of taking down information they were formally exposed to during their education. Think back to your first writing/grammar class and the first paper you had to write, how did the teacher have you organize your paper? Most likely, it was an outline. Now, the outline format works wonderfully for this instance and is a very powerful tool; however, that doesn’t mean it should be used in every situation. And, in practice, can actually have a negative impact on information retention when used for many notetaking situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this is often the only type of shorthand information drafting that students are exposed to and puts many students at a disadvantage. Not all students think in a linear, rigid manner; many are nonlinear thinkers and do no perform well when given monotonous lines of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to level the playing field and boost engagement, students should also be exposed to the wide variety of nonlinear notetaking methods! Nonlinearity is how the brain functions by default; thus, these methods are often very useful and easy for students to grasp. These nonlinear strategies utilize multiple colors, pictures, lines directly linking information, and keywords rather than strings of text (see Farrand et al. 2002)! Several studies (e.g. Beel 2009, D’Antoni 2010, Edwards and Cooper 2010, Pauk and Owens 2011, and many others) have investigated their usefulness in a wide array of scenarios and the positive feedback continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal favorite form of nonlinear notetaking is &lt;a href=&#34;www.mindmapping.com&#34;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;. Mind Maps begin with the central idea in the middle of the page and key information radiating out in all directions. Each radiating arm is then radiated further with increasely detailed information. The Mind Map can be as simple or elaborate as you choose and, best of all, &lt;strong&gt;it’s completely scaleable!&lt;/strong&gt; Each Mind Map from a given lesson can be envisioned as one radiating arm branching out from the central idea/topic of the class!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2017/images/MindMap.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind Maps are incredible assests for not only students, but teachers as well! I have used this strategy extensively in both my schooling and teaching settings. By continuosly changing colors and adding quick sketches to help explain the idea, students remain engaged in the classroom and can see direct links between information and how they fit together. This also achieves another goal, moving away from powerpoint slides. The plague of powerpoint slide presentations for instruction is a continuing issue in teh classroom, primarily at the college level. However, by using Mind Maps, or any other nonlinear form of notetaking, the teacher can build the notes &lt;strong&gt;along with the student&lt;/strong&gt; and help to avoid confusion of how information fits together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outline-form and other linear formats of notetaking have their place and uses (recipes, mapping out a paper, etc.); however, if the topic you are learning, or teaching, is not a linear construct then there is no reason to force linear notes to tell the story and provide the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as you move through your studies, or your career, consider exploring a new form of notetaking. Your brain will thank you and chances are you will be much more alert and engaged in the topic; you will likely also recall more of the information when/if it is needed later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
